I hear from lots of
people every day
who are concerned about how
their diet is affecting their health.
They need answers
based on facts.
In other words,
in the peer-reviewed
medical literature,
and that is what
I’m here for.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we take a deep dive
into drugs and supplements
that don’t work as advertised.
And we start with a deceptive
supplement called Prevagen.
Over the last twenty years or so,
Big Pharma has invested more
than a half trillion dollars
into dementia treatment research,
but so far to little avail.
In light of this,
many have turned to supplements.
An AARP commissioned survey found
that 36% of those 74 years and older
take a supplement for brain health,
to the tune of billions of dollars a year.
The most commonly marketed
brain supplement
was one I’d frankly
never heard of before: Prevagen.
Prevagen contains a protein
derived from a luminescent jellyfish
the company claims "has been
clinically shown to improve memory."
According to the company website,
“A landmark double-blind
and placebo controlled trial
demonstrated Prevagen
improved short-term memory,
learning, and delayed recall
over 90 days.”
But when you actually pull up the study,
not only did Prevagen fail to improve
memory, learning, or recall over placebo,
it failed to show a significant improvement
in any of the nine
measured cognitive tasks tested.
As an inquiry into Prevagen published by
the Center for Science in the Public Interest
was titled, “How Can This Memory Supplement
Flunk Its One Trial
and Still Be Advertised as Effective?”
And not just as effective but the #1
pharmacist recommended brand.
Considering the lack of sound
clinical evidence, how is that possible?
Presumably, they’re just as blitzed with
the same kind advertising as everyone else.
It’s no surprise the supplement
didn’t do anything
since the company’s own studies
showed the jellyfish protein
was rapidly digested
by stomach enzymes.
Of course, that didn’t stop them from
raking in more than $20 million a year.
Claiming the “marketers of Prevagen
preyed on the fears of older consumers
experiencing age-related memory loss,”
the Federal Trade Commission
and New York State’s Attorney General
filed a consumer protection complaint,
charging the company with making false
and unsubstantiated claims.
The AARP weighed in, accusing the company
of “deceiving millions of aging Americans.”
In a move straight out of
the Big Pharma aducanumab playbook,
the company went back and conducted
more than 30 post hoc analyses of the data
and found a few positive findings
on a few tasks for some subgroups.
This cherry-picking
of subgroups after-the-fact
is a classic example of manipulation
sometimes called “p-hacking”
or “data dredging”
that can be described
as “placing a bet on a horse
after watching the race.”
The makers of Prevagen settled a class action
lawsuit in 2020 with the FTC
over deceptive business practices
and false advertising.
Remarkably, though, the settlement allows them
to continue to market it
with the court-approved
disclaimer that claims
are “based on a clinical study
of subgroups of individuals …”
But with the amount of slicing
and dicing of data they did,
the chances of finding
at least one false positive
was estimated at 80 percent.
Prevagen may be more than
just a waste of money.
The manufacturer was cited
for failing to report
more than a thousand adverse events
related by consumers
to the Food and
Drug Administration (FDA).
Regulators can’t have it both ways, though.
If the jellyfish protein is digested away,
how can it pose a safety risk?
Because dietary supplements are too often
adulterated with contaminants.
FDA inspectors specifically cited
Prevagen’s manufacturing facilities
for “objectionable conditions or practices.”
A 2019 survey by Pew
found that more than half believed
that the Food and Drug Administration
requires supplements be tested for safety,
but that isn’t true.
One study of 24 supplements sold
as cognitive performance boosters
found that most claimed
an ingredient on the label
that wasn’t actually in the supplement,
and worse, 38 percent contained ingredients
not allowed in supplements
like prohibited drugs.
Another study of a dozen so-called
“brain health supplements”
similarly found 8 out of 12 were misbranded
(missing an ingredient
promised on the label),
and 10 out of 12
were deemed adulterated
(containing unlisted compounds,
for example caffeine
in a product that explicitly highlighted
all-caps ‘‘DECAFFEINATED’’ on the label).
Only 1 out of 12 was certiﬁed
to contain what it said it did.
The bottom line for Prevagen:
there is no acceptable evidence
that it's effective.
Patients should be advised
not to take it.
In our next story,
we look at the safety
and efficacy
of two of the newest
Alzheimer’s drug treatments.
Aducanumab, sold as Aduhelm,
is the first new drug
approved for Alzheimer’s treatment
in nearly 20 years.
It involves getting IV infusions of an antibody
that targets the amyloid plaque protein,
which represents a core brain pathology
in the disease.
After a phase 1 study found
no change in the placebo group,
but a dramatic reduction in amyloid plaque
burden at different doses of the drug,
they jumped straight to phase 3:
two randomized controlled trials
to put it to the test
on thousands of Alzheimer’s patients.
Unfortunately, both trials
were stopped early
after a “futility analysis”
deemed them failures,
as cognition and function continued
to decline in the treatment groups.
That shouldn’t be surprising
since over the last 20 years
there have been more than
20 amyloid-targeting therapies
that have universally failed
to offer meaningful cognitive beneﬁt
for people with Alzheimer’s disease.
In fact, a 2022 investigation
into a seminal paper
implicating amyloid as a causal factor
in Alzheimer's alleged
“shockingly blatant” data fraud,
which has further tarnished
the reputation of the amyloid theory.
So, no surprise Aduhelm flopped,
but what happened next
was surprising indeed.
Just when the drug’s prospects seemed dead,
Biogen, the drug company that developed it,
launched a secret campaign,
code-named “Project Onyx,”
to use back channels to convince
the Food and Drug Administration
to approve it anyway.
They went back through the data and found
the subset of patients in one of the trials
that had a 0.39 increase on an
18-point scale of cognitive function.
This was well below the minimal standard
for clinical significance
(judged to be at least 1 or 2 full points),
and the same subset,
at the same dose, in the other study
they funded failed to find even that effect.
This kind of post-hoc,
after-the-fact data dredging
is like “firing a shotgun at a barn
and then painting a target
around the bullet holes,”
as one FDA committee
statistician put it.
FDA reviewers thoroughly
demolished Biogen’s re-analysis,
concluding “there is no compelling
substantialevidence
of treatment effect or disease slowing … ”
The American Academy of Neurology noted
that 35 percent of those getting aducanumab
suffered swelling or bleeding in the brain
within the first four months of treatment—
one in three—ten times more than
those in the placebo group.
So, not surprisingly, not a single member
of the FDA expert advisory panel
voted in favor of approval (10 out of 11
voted against with 1 “uncertain”).
Yet the FDA ignored
its own advisory committee,
and in 2021 approved
the drug anyway.
The FDA admitted the submitted data
“left residual uncertainties
regarding clinical benefit” and so
couldn’t give it the standard approval,
which involves a designation
that the drug is safe and effective.
Instead, they used an
“accelerated approval” pathway
that allows drugs to be accepted
on the basis of surrogate markers,
in this case amyloid clearance.
But more than two dozen other
amyloid-targeting treatments flopped.
And despite convincing plaque reduction,
there were no clinical improvements
or even worsening of the disease.
The FDA approval of aducanumab proved
to be one of the most controversial
in recent memory.
The approval despite near unanimous
opposition by its own expert committee
is virtually unprecedented, leading three
of the committee members
to resign in protest,
one of them called it
“probably the worst drug approval decision
in recent US history.”
The response from the scientific community
may best be summed up by a commentary
written by the head of the American
Geriatrics Society entitled,
“My head just exploded …”
The FDA did stipulate that Biogen
would have to run a “post-marketing” trial
proving that the drug
actually has some benefit,
but has until 2030 to report the results.
Meanwhile, Biogen is charging
$56,000 per person per year for the drug,
with out-of-pocket expenses estimated
at up to $11,000 annually.
And this doesn’t include
the costs of IV administration
or the sequential $4,000
to $7,000 MRI scans
needed to monitor
for the brain bleeds and swelling.
Yeah, the risks far exceed
any likely benefits,
but shouldn’t patients and their families
be able to make up their own minds?
The problem is that
the FDA stamp of approval implies
aducanumab is safe and effective,
when at the current time
it appears to be neither.
The official position statement of the
American Medical Directors Association,
which specializes
is long-term care facilities,
is that the drug is “likely to have
extraordinarily negative consequences”
for the millions living
with dementia in this country.
The European equivalent of the FDA does not
seem as easily swayed by Big Pharma,
recommending refusal of the drug.
I mean, that’s the whole point
of drug regulation,
as one of the former FDA committee
members who resigned put it:
a responsibility to help vulnerable
patients and their families,
not just from sketchy drugs
but also from false hopes.
A congressional investigation concluded
FDA approval of aducanumab
was “rife with irregularities,”
raising “serious concerns
about FDA’s lapses in protocol
and Biogen’s disregard of efficacy.”
Of course, that didn’t stop the FDA
from their 2023 accelerated approval
of a similar antibody,
lecanemab (sold as Lequembi),
of similar questionable
efficacy and safety.
Did you know that
there's little guarantee
that a dietary supplement
will actually contain
what is advertised
on the packaging?
Here’s the story.
In a video I did a few years ago,
I talked about how press releases
about the latest science coming
out of even top medical centers
were filled with
overstatements and omissions.
Medical journal press releases
suffered from similar problems,
and press releases from the
drug companies themselves
were no different, filled with
hype and exaggeration.
What about press releases
issued by the supplements industry?
Not even the companies
that published the studies,
but like trade organizations
for the multi-billion-dollar
dietary supplement industry?
Researchers found that 100% of
supplements industry press releases
contained "spin," meaning strategies
to hype or denigrate findings
to distort the results
of clinical studies.
And here's the crazy part:
industry press releases advocated
supplement use in response
to more than 90%
of even the studies that
reported no benefit or harm.
A study comes out showing a
supplement is actually bad for you,
and the vast majority of
independent institutions like
the National Institutes of Health
or mainstream media stories
are like "don't take it."
Duh. But the industry trade
organizations are like, "Harm?
Go for it! Buy an extra bottle."
It is, therefore, likely that the
propagation of the spin-enriched
industry press releases contributes
to the ongoing, and even burgeoning,
enthusiasm for use of supplements
in the face of accumulating evidence
of most of their ineffectiveness
and, in some cases, harm.
In some cases, people are paying
to make themselves sick.
Sadly, the science may not even
matter to many supplement users.
Most dietary supplement users said
that they would be minimally influenced
by independent, taxpayer-funded
studies contradicting
the efficacy claims of
supplement manufacturers.
Only a minority of users said they
would stop taking a supplement
if public health authorities stated
that it was just a waste of money.
The iconic image of the snake oil
salesman was actually a real dude:
Clark "the Rattlesnake King" Stanley
in 1916.
Turns out that Stanley's snake oil,
in fact, contained no snake oil at all
but rather just like spicy
mothballs and turpentine,
prosecuted under the newly enacted
Pure Food and Drug Act,
and ultimately fined a
lofty sum of $20 bucks.
And a century later, here we are
with snake oil coming out our ears,
a vast number of supplements marketed
and sold without routine oversight.
Now, the supplement industry
bristles at such talk, saying that
the supplement industry is
regulated to protect consumers.
And it's true there are definitely
laws on the books, but the ability
of regulators to successfully carry
out this mission is hampered
by the sheer number of products.
The FDA estimates there are more
than 85,000 dietary supplement
products currently available
in the U.S. alone.
So there's the sheer number,
the under reporting of adverse
side effects, the difficulty
of successfully prosecuting
cases against offenders,
and the ease with which
suppliers can rebrand products
removed from the shelves
have led to a largely
unregulated environment.
In the real world, there is little
guarantee that a supplement
will even contain what is
advertised on the packaging and
not contain unlisted ingredients,
potentially leading to significant
harms, resulting in an estimated
23,000 ER visits every year.
Now, of course, prescription drugs
don't just sicken but kill many more,
making them perhaps the
third leading cause of death,
wiping out more than
100,000 Americans, but still,
the less death and disability,
the better.
Dietary supplements
are often adulterated
with undeclared pharmaceuticals,
which could represent
an enormous risk to consumers, most
often found in erectile dysfunction,
weight loss, diabetes, and high
blood pressure supplements.
But wait a second.
What about
supplement manufacturers
who say they have independent,
third-party certification of purity?
There is a practice called
"dry labbing," a dirty little secret
of the supplements industry,
where quality assurance labs
just rubber stamp fake documents.
And if you think that's outrageous,
check out the story of BMPEA.
A researcher at Harvard published
a paper replicating prior research
from the FDA detecting a designer
amphetamine-like stimulant,
beta-methylphenylethylamine,
in various U.S. supplements
sold in the United States.
In response, one of the offenders,
Hi-Tech Pharmaceuticals,
manufacturers of weight
loss supplements like
Black Widow and Yellow Scorpion,
sued the Harvard researcher
for libel, slander, and product
disparagement, originally to the
tune of $200 million in damages.
This was all documented
in a piece by STAT,
which is an excellent source
of medical journalism
that I recommend.
The head of Hi-Tech openly
admitted that he was
"hoping that we were
able to silence this guy."
And while ultimately unsuccessful in
court, Hi-Tech's lawsuit effectively
sent a warning to other researchers.
In fact, Hi-Tech's CEO is
attributed as saying,
he "hope[s] that the long and costly
legal battle will scare away
other academics from investigating
the supplement industry."
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
premiering at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.